Guide to the A.B. Guthrie Jr. Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, Series II
  - Articles
    - "The American West," Life, 6 December 1958, working draft, typescript original with carbon inserts; typescript carbon, 1958 Dec 2
    - "The Therefore Hog," Western Writers of America 1959 anthology, typescript carbon, undated (Box 33, Folder 422)
    - "Old Bear--Young Man," typescript carbon, 1961 Jan 16
    - "Rima Revisited," typescript carbon with annotations; Country Beautiful, typescript carbon, 1961
    - Untitled [on Choteau], typescript carbon, 1961 Jun 12
    - "The Image," Country Beautiful 1963, typescript carbon; typescript carbon with annotations, undated
    - "Choteau, Montana," [July-August 1954], correspondence; typescript carbon; typescript carbon and original with annotations; "This is America," typescript carbon with annotations, 1963 Sep 28 (Box 33, Folder 423)
    - "What Every Family Needs--A Hideaway From Life's Pressures," Family Weekly, tearsheet, 1969 Jan 26
    - Harper Dictionary of Contemporary Usage. Correspondence, 1971 (Box 33, Folder 424)
    - "The Wonder of the West," Sunday Herald Traveler, (Lexington, Kentucky) Book Guide section, 1971 Mar 14 (Box 33, Folder 425)
    - "Reflections on a Flush Toilet," typescript carbon with annotations; typescript original with annotations, 1973 Mar
    - Untitled, "published in April 1974 Travel and Leisure," typescript original with annotation, undated
    - "Message to DeVoto," published in Montana Outdoors (May June 1974), typescript original with annotations, with accompany TLS from Harper's, undated
    - "Western Variety Show," typescript original; with publication, 1975 Aug 4
    - "Original for Montana Magazine," typescript carbon with annotations, 1987 Sep (Box 33, Folder 426)
    - "Original for Clair Backes [published in Growing Up Western]," typescript original with annotations; second copy. typescript photocopy, 1987
    - "Loving Montana," Written for Nature Conservancy to be used on celebrating statehood in 1989, typescript original with annotations, 1987
    - "Original for Rick Graetz," introduction to We Montanans, typescript original with annotations, 1988 Aug 26
    - "Written for Mother Earth News 1989," typescript original with annotations, undated
    - "Originals of copy for Montana Vol. 1 for Rick Graetz," typescript originals with annotations, 1989 (Box 33, Folder 427)
  - Introductions and Reviews
    After the success of The Big Sky and The Way West, Guthrie was frequently asked to contribute introductions to books by colleagues and to review both fiction and scholarly works on the American West. The citations in this section are Guthrie's own. Undated manuscripts are followed by dated manuscripts, arranged chronologically.
    - "Introduction to Western Story: The Recollections of Charley O'Kieffe," typescript carbon, undated (Box 33, Folder 428)
    - "Introduction to Owen Wister Out West: His Journals and Letters," typescript carbon, undated
    - "Introduction to Athearn's biography of Thomas Meagher," typescript carbon, undated
    - "Introduction to Sand in A Whirlwind by Ferrol Egan," typescript original with annotations, undated
    - "Introduction to Time-Life's The Rocky Mountain West," typescript carbon, undated
    - "Introduction to American Odyssey," typescript carbon, undated
    - "Introduction to book on Montana published by Country Beautiful," typescript original with annotations, undated
    - "Introduction to a book on Sliver's Warrington," typescript original with annotations, undated
    - "Introduction to Prairie Schooner Days," typescript original with annotations, undated
    - "Introduction to When You and I Were Young, Whitefish," typescript photocopy with annotations, undated
    - "Introduction to David Petersen's Lewis & Clark," typescript original with annotations, 1988
    - "Introduction to Bloody Bozeman," typescript original with annotations, 1982
    - "Introduction to William Gardner Bell's Life of Will James," typescript original with annotations, 1986
    - "Introduction to Steve Smith's Biography of Dorothy Johnson," typescript original with annotations, 1984
    - "Introduction to Booklet on Glacier and Waterton National Parks," typescript original with annotations, 1984
    - "Introduction to Reissue of Robert Flynn's North to Yesterday," typescript original with annotations, 1984
    - "Introduction to Reprints of James Willard Schultz's Work for Confluence Press, Lewiston, Idaho, Written October 1983," typescript original with annotations, 1983 Oct
    - Review for Saturday Review of Land of Giants: The Drive to the Pacific Northwest, 1750-1850 by David Lavender, typescript carbon, undated
    - Review for Montana Magazine of History, of Stirrup High by Walt Coburn, typescript carbon, undated
    - Review for Montana Magazine of History, of Strange Empire by Joseph Kinsey Howard, typescript carbon, undated
    - Untitled, [introduction to Last of the Mohicans], typescript photocopy, undated (Box 33, Folder 429)
    - "Introduction," typescript photocopy with annotations, undated
  - Speeches
    The notes for and drafts of many of Guthrie's speeches are located in this section. Many manuscripts are untitled, as Guthrie sometimes delivered several versions or partial versions of the same talk, or spoke informally from notes. David Peterson drew on the speeches for his compilation of Guthrie's environmental essays, Big Sky, Fair Land (1988). Recordings of some talks are found in Audio and Video Recordings.
    - Letters to the Editor, 1954, undated (Box 33, Folder 430)
    - "Bozeman Heads English Department-- Western Region," typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 33, Folder 431)
    - Incomplete, typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 33, Folder 432)
    - "Story of Mary Lizzie and Dandelion Wine," typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 33, Folder 433)
    - "Watt-Mose Incident," typescript carbon, undated (Box 33, Folder 434)
    - Untitled, typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 33, Folder 435)
    - Untitled, typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 33, Folder 436)
    - Untitled, typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 33, Folder 437)
    - "London Obsession," typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 33, Folder 438)
    - Untitled, typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 33, Folder 439)
    - Untitled, holograph pencil, (on blank check), undated (Box 33, Folder 440)
    - Untitled, typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 33, Folder 441)
    - Untitled, typescript carbon with annotations, 1940 (Box 33, Folder 442)
    - Untitled, typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 33, Folder 443)
    - "Anything Can Happen in Montana!," typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 33, Folder 444)
    - "Earl W. Martell, Publications & News Service, MSU," typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 33, Folder 445)
    - Untitled, typescript original and carbon composite, undated (Box 33, Folder 446)
    - Untitled, typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 33, Folder 447)
    - Untitled, typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 33, Folder 448)
    - Untitled, typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 33, Folder 449)
    - Untitled, typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 33, Folder 450)
    - "What Attracts Me to Montana?," typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 34, Folder 451)
    - Untitled, typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 34, Folder 452)
    - "Instructions From Home to Talk About Hollywood," holograph outline and typescript original speech with annotations, undated (Box 34, Folder 453)
    - Untitled, typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 34, Folder 454)
    - Untitled, typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 34, Folder 455)
    - Untitled, typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 34, Folder 456)
    - "From A Talk By A.B. Guthrie Jr., Who Received the 1948 Award From the Friends of American Writers," mimeographed, undated (Box 34, Folder 457)
    - "Copy of Talk Made May 24, 1950, at Testimonial Dinner," typescript carbon with annotations, undated (Box 34, Folder 458)
    - "Needed: A Western Tradition--Remarks by A.B. Guthrie Jr., Western States Tourist Director's Conference, the Broadmoor, Colorado Springs, March 3, 1959," typescript original with annotations, 2 different copies, undated (Box 34, Folder 459)
    - "Talk for Western States Tourist Director's Conference, Colorado Springs, for Life magazine." Typescript carbon, 1959 Mar 3 (Box 34, Folder 460)
    - "Cancer Meeting, Butte--Sunday AM, February 15, 1959," typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 34, Folder 461)
    - "Reflections in Passing, College of Idaho, January 27, 1967," typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 34, Folder 462)
    - "Autobiographical bit written for Commonwealth Club of California, June 8, 1966, commemorating The Blue Hen's Chick," typescript carbon, undated
    - "Speech with variations given in whole or in part at Bozeman, at Billings, at Missoula Friends of the Library, at Pocatello, at Sheridan, at Gillette," typescript original, 1971 (Box 34, Folder 463)
    - "Remarks Made at Claim Staking Museum of the Rockies," typescript original with annotations, 1971 Nov 6 (Box 34, Folder 464)
    - "Speech Delivered to Unitarian Church, Spring 1972," typescript original with annotations; "Remarks Made Before Unitarians," typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 34, Folder 465)
    - "Why Write About the West," talk made before Western Literature Association, Jackson Hole, typescript original with annotations, 1972 Oct 6 (Box 34, Folder 466)
    - Untitled, Land Use Conference, Billings, typescript original, 1973 Nov 10 (Box 34, Folder 467)
    - "Notes for Talk to Pacific Northwest History Conference, April 1973, Bozeman, Montana," typescript original, undated (Box 34, Folder 468)
    - "Intro to Movie--Bozeman Outfit-- Gallatin Canyon, Elizabeth Hurley," typescript original with annotations, 1974 Aug 16 (Box 34, Folder 469)
    - "Address Before Environmental Reporters, Missoula, Montana, December 13, 1974," typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 34, Folder 470)
    - "Talk Made At Annual Banquet, Bozeman Chamber of Commerce, January 17, 1974," typescript original with annotations. With newspaper clipping covering the talk, undated (Box 34, Folder 471)
    - "Notes for Comments at Land-Use Panel, Missoula Spring Festival of the Arts, May 2, 1974--Excerpts used for 2 minute film talk for Spokane Expo," typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 34, Folder 472)
    - "Address--League of Women Voters-- Hamilton, Montana, December 5, 1974," typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 34, Folder 473)
    - "Recorded October 15, 1974, to accompany slides about Montana Land Use and Abuse," typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 34, Folder 474)
    - "Speech Given at Helena, October 25?, 1975, Historical Conference," typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 34, Folder 475)
    - "Speech by A.B. Guthrie Jr.--Writing Workshop for people over 57, August 8, 1975, Carnahan House, University of Kentucky," photocopy typescript, undated (Box 34, Folder 476)
    - "Speech by Bud, Writers Workshop, University of Kentucky, Aug. 8, 1975," typescript original with annotations., undated (Box 34, Folder 477)
    - "Material Used at Writing Conf. University of Kentucky, Aug. 1975" typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 34, Folder 478)
    - "Copy of Speech Given to Annual Meeting, Museum of the Rockies, May 17, 1976," typescript carbon Includes Rough Draft MS, undated (Box 34, Folder 479)
    - "Speech Delivered at Eastern Montana College, June 14, 1976, Leadership Conference," typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 34, Folder 480)
    - "Notes for Some European Speeches, 1977, American Specialists," holograph notes, undated (Box 34, Folder 481)
    - "Death of A Trout Stream," Trout Unlimited National Meeting, Bozeman, Montana (final), typescript original with annotations. Includes Rough Draft MS., undated (Box 34, Folder 482)
    - "Introduction to Reading, Missoula, May 1979--Reading Last Chapter of The Last Valley," typescript original and photocopy, undated (Box 34, Folder 483)
    - "Speech Given in Lewistown, Montana, March 27, 1980 to Symposium on Family Farm," typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 34, Folder 484)
    - "Speech--Great Falls Library, March 1981," typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 34, Folder 485)
    - "Friends of the Library, Missoula?, March 1981? or March 1982?," typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 34, Folder 486)
    - "Acceptance Remarks, Governor's Award," typescript original with annotations; "Statement for Governor's Award, Slide Number One Show, January 1982," typescript original with annotations, autograph, 1982 Jan 27 (Box 34, Folder 487)
    - "Original Talk Given 1982, Denver-- Tucson. Book/Author Luncheons," typescript original with annotations; also reader's copy of same talk, undated (Box 34, Folder 488)
    - "Here and Hereafter, Bozeman, Montana, May 1983," typescript original with annotations. Typescript original with annotations, 1983 Apr 29 (Box 34, Folder 489)
    - "Speech Delivered April 3, 1985, Carroll College," typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 34, Folder 490)
    - "The Historical Novel--Lewis & Clark Speech Mighty Discounted," n.d., typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 34, Folder 491)
    - "Remarks to be Read at College of Idaho on Award of Doctorate to Me, in Absentia, May 31, 1986," typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 34, Folder 492)
    - "Statement for Montana Arts Council, 1986," typescript original, undated (Box 34, Folder 493)
    - "Written for Nature Conservancy 1987," typescript, undated (Box 34, Folder 494)
    - "Original (not complete) of Material Delivered (taped) at Writers Conference, Pine Butte Guest Ranch, October 13, 1990," typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 34, Folder 495)
    - "Crotchets," typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 34, Folder 496)
    - "Another Version of Generic Speech," typescript original. "Earlier Version, Generic Speech," n.d., typescript original, undated (Box 34, Folder 497)
    - Untitled, typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 34, Folder 498)
    - "Speech Given at Grinnell College," typescript carbon, undated (Box 34, Folder 499)
    - "Twenty-six Years After," Montana State University, published by Jane Graham, 1949 Jul 29 (Box 34, Folder 500)
  - Other Writings
    This section has two parts: Prose and Poetry. Prose consists largely of drafts of material left unpublished at Guthrie's death and unidentified working drafts. The poetry, much of it untitled, is in the original order.
    - Prose
      - "You, Too," typescript original with annotations, and carbon copy of same with no annotations, undated (Box 34, Folder 501)
      - "Essay--Read Magazine," typescript carbon, undated
      - "The Ones Who Can't," typescript carbon; typescript original, undated
      - "Dead Dog," typescript carbon, undated
      - "Victory Garden," typescript original with annotations, undated
      - "Three Nips and a Calf," typescript carbon, undated
      - "I Ordered Pot Roast," Untitled Western Piece for The Philadelphia Inquirer, typescript carbon, undated
      - "The Little Blackout," typescript original, undated (Box 34, Folder 502)
      - "They'll Be There," typescript carbon, undated
      - "They'll Be There," typescript photocopy, undated (Box 35, Folder 503)
      - "History in Fiction," typescript carbon, undated (Box 35, Folder 504)
      - "How to Stock a Pond," typescript carbon, undated
      - "Straw Boss," typescript carbon, undated
      - Untitled, typescript original, undated
      - "Case of Bad Medicine," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
      - "On Being It in a Documentary," typescript original; second copy, typescript original with annotations, undated
      - "The Rocky Mountain West--Montana," typescript original with annotations, undated
      - "The Choice," typescript carbon, undated
      - "The Sled," typescript original with annotations, undated
      - "Initials on a Tree," typescript carbon with annotations; second copy identical without annotations, undated
      - "The Stinkless Skunk," typescript carbon, undated
      - "One Man's Lane," typescript carbon, undated
      - "Some Things to Go," typescript original (reverse side is letter from John Hess); typescript original with annotations, undated
      - Untitled, [Bob Marshall Wilderness area], typescript original with annotations, undated
      - Untitled, typescript original, undated
      - "Start on Wilderness," typescript original with annotations, undated
      - "Sing a Song of Dachshund," typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 35, Folder 505)
      - "Sing a Song of Dachshund," typescript original with annotations, undated
      - "The Swamp and Company," typescript original with annotations, undated
      - "Rough Draft to Accompany Caemden Records Reading from The Big Sky," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
      - "Dinosaurs Almost in Our Backyard," typescript original with annotations, 1986
      - "Copy of Unpublished Piece Originally Written for Aperture," typescript photocopy; typescript carbon, 1988
    - Poetry
      - "Freedom of speech...", holograph photocopy, undated (Box 35, Folder 506)
      - "A Love Song for My Lady 21st Anniversary," typescript original, undated
      - "Twenty-second Anniversary," typescript photocopy, undated
      - "Carol my honey, my lamb...," typescript photocopy, 1990 May 14
      - "For Carol," typescript photocopy, undated
      - "Wind Around the Cabin," typescript photocopy, undated
      - "Twin Lakes Fourth of July (Again)," typescript original, with author's signature, undated
      - "Written for Forest Service," original typescript original with annotations, 1986
      - Untitled, calligraphy photocopy, undated
      - "Island," typescript carbon, undated
      - "Twin Lakes Winter," typescript carbon, undated
      - "Twin Lakes Hunter," typescript carbon, undated
      - "Twin Lakes Visitor," typescript carbon, undated
      - "Little Peggy," typescript original, undated
      - "I Can Remember When A Licked Stamp Stuck," typescript carbon, undated
      - "Old Friends and new, my welcome...", typescript original with annotations, undated
      - "Tenth Anniversary," typescript original, undated
      - "Bird in the Hand," [written under pseudonym J.T.], tearsheet from Sunday Herald Leader (Lexington, Kentucky), with holograph note by ABG
      - "Seventh Cavalry," sold to American West, typescript original with annotations, 1985 Apr
      - "Five thousand dead...," typescript original. "Original of poem written (but not sent) to Richard Hugo." Inscribed by ABG, undated
- Personal Papers, Series III
  This series contains material relating to Guthrie's finances, medical records, and educational activities. The bank accounts document Guthrie's residences in Kentucky and Montana.
  - Educational
    - Montana State University transcript, 1923 (Box 36, Folder 507)
    - Supervised Story Writing School, 1943-45 (Box 36, Folder 508)
  - Financial
    - Bank Accounts, 1941-46 (Box 36, Folder 509)
    - Residences, 1940-71, undated (Box 36, Folder 510)
    - Receipts, Assessments, Bills of Sale, 1937-50, undated (Box 36, Folder 511)
    - Insurance, 1957-60, undated (Box 36, Folder 512)
    - Self-Employment Tax, 1959-60 (Box 36, Folder 513)
    - Taxes, 1961 (Box 36, Folder 514)
  - Medical
    - Receipts, 1973 (Box 36, Folder 515)
- Subject Files, Series IV
  - American Specialist Trip--Europe 1977
    - Correspondence, itineraries, lecture notes on the American West, 1977 (Box 37, Folder 516-517)
  - Biographical Information
    - Newspaper clippings, promotional material and assorted autobiographical musings, undated (Box 37, Folder 518-523)
  - Civic Involvement
    - Montana State Board of Education. Correspondence, 1955-57 (Box 37, Folder 524)
  - Honors and Awards
    - Correspondence, speech, and programs, 1966-82 (Box 37, Folder 525)
    - "Speech Given Before Governor's Arts Awards Banquet, by H.W. Luthin," typescript photocopy. Program, invitation, press releases, and correspondence, 1982 Jan
    - National Cowboy Hall of Fame, Western Heritage Award, undated
    - Utah State University, undated
    - Indiana State University, undated
    - University of Montana, Friends of the Library, undated
    - Western American Literature Association, undated
    - Phi Sigma Kappa fraternity, undated
    - "A.B. Guthrie Literary Contribution Award." Presented by Mountain Plains Library Association., 1987
    - A.B. Guthrie Jr., Testimonial Dinner, University of Kentucky. Correspondence, 1950. Correspondents include: Dwight D. Eisenhower, Edward Lasker, Sidney Katz, Governor Earl Clements, Louis Lyons, Grayson L. Kirk, Fletcher Martin, Helen Cruthers, William Rainey, Bernard DeVoto, Joe Howard, Mildred Walker, Lee Keedick, Maxwell Aley, John F. Day, Paul Hughes. Note: See Audio and Video Recordings list for audio recording of the testimonial dinner. (Box 37, Folder 526)
    - Other Honors and Awards, undated (Box 37, Folder 527)
  - Kennedy Fund
    - Correspondence, Bank statements, lists, and legal papers relating to Mike Kennedy's case., 1966 (Box 37, Folder 528)
  - Motion Pictures
    Beginning in 1951, Guthrie journeyed to Hollywood and, for the moment, put his novel writing on hold, to write the screenplay to Shane for George Stevens Productions. The film was released in 1953. He returned to Hollywood from time to time in attempts to write screenplays for The Way West (United Artists, 1967), The Kentuckian (Twentieth Century-Fox, 1955), and a failed attempt at penning These Thousand Hills (Twentieth Century-Fox, 1956). He would also write unproduced pilots for television. The correspondence (frequently detailed) deals with these productions as well as with explorations into various consulting assignments and motion picture projects.
    - General Correspondence. Correspondents include: Ed Lasker (RKO Radio Pictures), Frank P. Rosenberg (20th Century-Fox), Ivan Moffat (producer, George Stevens Productions), Monte Brice (producer, Paramount Pictures), Ned Brown (MCA Agency), Jerry Wald (Vice President, Columbia Pictures), Jean Hersholt, Arthur Kramer (story editor, 20th Century-Fox), Julian Blaustein (independent producer), David Weisbart, (producer, 20th Century-Fox), William Rowland (Paramount Pictures), and A.B. Guthrie Jr. Re: contract negotiations, screen credit arbitration, story ideas, consulting opportunities, and script revisions for Shane, The Big Sky, These Thousand Hills, The Kentuckian, and The Way West., 1947-55 (Box 37, Folder 529)
    - General Correspondence, 1956-59 (Box 37, Folder 530)
    - General Correspondence. Correspondents include: Monte Brice, Jerry Bresler (Columbia Pictures), Burt Lancaster, David Weisbart, William Rowland, Hal Kanter (20th Century-Fox), Ben Benjamin, James R. Webb (screenwriter), Philip Miller (Ashley Famous Agency), Harold Hecht (producer, Harold Hecht Company), Budd Schulberg (producer), and A.B. Guthrie Jr. Re: story ideas, script revisions, consulting opportunities and The Way West, also television project "Sun Prairie.", 1960-74 (Box 38, Folder 531)
    - Ben Benjamin/Famous Artists Agency. Correspondence. Re: extensive detail relative to Guthrie's credited and uncredited/unproduced screenwriting, contract negotiations, and employment opportunities in motion pictures and television., 1950-57 (Box 38, Folder 532)